<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A matter of moment: or, A case of waight As great as euer was any, to be pleaded and examined in the hall of the heart and conscience of euery Christian at all times, before the receiuing of the Lords Supper. Touching that waightie charge of the Apostle Paul, in the I. Cor. II.28. Let euery man examine himselfe, and so let him eate of this bread and drinke of this cup. Set forth dialogue wise.</title>
            <author>Tye, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837588</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837588</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1012:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A matter of moment: or, A case of waight As great as euer was any, to be pleaded and examined in the hall of the heart and conscience of euery Christian at all times, before the receiuing of the Lords Supper. Touching that waightie charge of the Apostle Paul, in the I. Cor. II.28. Let euery man examine himselfe, and so let him eate of this bread and drinke of this cup. Set forth dialogue wise.</title>
                  <author>Tye, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Raworth, for Henry Bell, and are to be sold at his shop on Holborone-hill, neere the signe of the Croste-keyes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Tye.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Examinations before the Lords Supper.</note>
                  <note>Includes, with caption title: A prayer and meditation before the receiuing of the holy communion, in no wise to be forgotten in thy chamber priuately.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MATTER of moment: OR, <hi>A Caſe of Waight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As great as euer was any, to <hi>be pleaded and examined in the Hall</hi> of the heart and Conſcience of euery Chriſtian at all times, before the receiuing of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Touching that waightie charge of the Apoſtle</hi> Paul, in the 1. Cor. 11.28. <hi>Let euery man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this bread and drinke of this cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth Dialogue wiſe.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>Robert Raworth,</hi> for <hi>Henry Bell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop on Holborne-hill, neere the ſigne of the Croſſe-keyes. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the moſt high <hi>and mighty Prince,</hi> Henry, Prince of Great Britaine, Sonne <hi>and Heire Apparant to our</hi> Soueraigne Lord the King.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt gratious and happy</hi> Prince: not long ſithence a certaine Religious Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman asked me two que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions touching thoſe weightie wordes of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>1. Corin. 11. Let euery man therefore exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this bread, &amp; drinke of this cup.</hi> The firſt was: whether euery Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an be bound of neceſsitie to examine themſelues before they doe receiue the Lords Supper or not.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:3"/>
            <p>The ſecond was: wherein that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of euery ones ſelfe dooth conſiſt, or what the points bee, which euery Chriſtian by this examination muſt find in himſelfe, before hee can receiue ahe Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Two queſtions, deſeruing a very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full anſwer, becauſe they are as great and as needfull, as euer any can be in theſe daies.</p>
            <p>The former toucheth the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Atheist, who is wont, to preſume to the Lordes holy Supper, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what hee doeth. The latter concernes the blinde ignorant ſort, which are wont thither to flocke (it is a wonder to ſee) not knowing, what they doe. By both which, this great Sacrament is euery where fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſed, and the breaches of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and the ruines of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by become moſt lamentable.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe, at that time with
<pb facs="tcp:1920:3"/> my beſt endeuour, I anſwered the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions in our priuate conference toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with all ſuch doubts and obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as did ariſe from, and were occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by that our ſpeech. Sithence, I handled the ſame abroad by publike preaching, as occaſion was offered, which heard: I vnderſtood, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were delighted in the diuine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. Many much reioyced at the plaine and eaſie order, affirming, that they had red ſundry godly writings of the ſame argument, &amp; heard diuers learnedly entreating of thoſe words of the Apoſtle: but that the way to the performance of this duty of examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was neuer tracted ſo plain, ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſo eaſie. Laſtly therefore, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what hurt the hiding vp of this ſimple Talent may do: &amp; againe, what gaine and profite the occupying of the ſame abroad by Sea &amp; land, through Gods bleſsing might bring vnto his Church,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:4"/> I thought beſt for that end to put pen to paper, and humbly to dedicate the ſame to you (moſt noble Prince) eſpecially for two cauſes,</p>
            <p>The firſt and chiefest is: after your moſt noble Father, our moſt gratious Soueraigne King <hi>Iames,</hi> whom God long preſerue, you are our next glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome hope, to gouerne theſe Realmes and Kingdomes with wholeſome Lawes, and chiefly with ſincere loue vnto Gods true Religion, whereof this little booke containes a part: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (I hope) your gratious clemencie will not onely take well in worth my good will and meaning, but alſo will put thereto the ſignet of your prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly licence and allowance, vnder which this little Talent, <hi>Quod ſentio, quam ſit exiguum,</hi> may paſſe, be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and vſed, the rather becauſe it is the marchandiſe of heauens king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:4"/>
            <p>The other cauſe is: as my grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father Doctor <hi>Tye</hi> was Tutor to Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> afterward King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixt: ſo likewiſe, though I neither deſire, nor deſerue the like place, yet am I glad (moſt noble Prince) to ſhew any token of mine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained hartie dutie &amp; loue vnto your Grace, whereby (ſo farre as I may be bold) I might bid you hearty welcome into theſe your Fathers Dominions: wherein in my daily praiers, I humbly craue of almightie God, in all happie peace to eſtabliſh his excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and his royall Progenie euen to the worlds end.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your HIGHNESSE,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>in all humbleneſſe of duty to be commanded,</hi> William Tye.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A Dialogue,</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Examination before <hi>the receiuing of the Lords Supper. Lately had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>A chriſtian Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> making obiection, <hi>&amp;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Miniſter making anſwer.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiection.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, I haue had a purpoſe to conferre with you in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of waight, touching the Lords holy Supper, if I might finde you at leyſure.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſwer.</speaker>
               <p>And I (good Sir) in a matter ſo waightie would gladly heare you. I pray you ſay on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That worthy Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtle written to the Corinthians, the eleuenth chapter hath theſe wordes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1920:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let euery man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this bread, and drinke of this cuppe. Touching that <hi>Examination</hi> of euerie ones ſelfe, I would craue your reſolution in two points.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>My beſt endeuour is ready, what be thoſe two points?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt I would be reſolued, whether euerie one bee of neceſsitie bound to examine themſelues before they doe eate of the bread and drinke of the cup in the Lords Supper: And if it be ſo. Secondly, I would know wherein that examination of ones ſelfe doth conſiſt, or for what euerie one muſt examine themſelues? For an infinite number through infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, doubting of the former, doe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether neglect this examination of themſelues: and many againe, willing to performe it, know not how to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the latter, namely, wherein, or for what they ſhuld examin the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Euerie one is bound of neceſſitie to examine himſelfe before he doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note>To your firſt queſtion I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer affirmatiuely, namely, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie
<pb facs="tcp:1920:6"/> one is bound of neceſſitie to examine himſelfe, before he doe eate of the bread and drinke of the cuppe in the Lords Supper. and I hope, none ſo wicked to deny it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>For my part I doe neither denie it, nor doubt of it: but yet I would bee better reſolued by ſome reaſons that it is ſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>If reaſons you would haue in ſo plaine a caſe, then marke them well. I will proue it vnto you by Reaſons, and thoſe of force.<note place="margin">The firſt Reaſon.</note> The firſt may bee drawne from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Apoſtle in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking by the ſpirit of God, commanded euerie one to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine</hi> himſelfe before he doe receiue the Lords Supper. Therefore euery one is bound of neceſſitie to doe it. And if there were none other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, this only would be of ſufficient force to proue it. But heare a ſecond,<note place="margin">The ſecond Reaſon.</note> thus: Euerie one is bound by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie to know before hand, whether he ſhall eate and drinke the Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:1920:7"/> Supper worthily, that is, as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſuch a ſupper to bee eaten and drunke, not peruerting the right and pure vſe thereof.</p>
               <p>But none can know that, except they examine themſelues.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is cléere, that euery one is bound of neceſſity to examine himſelfe, before hee doe eate and drinke the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third Reaſon.</note>A third reaſon is ſet downe by the Apoſtle himſelfe in that <hi>1. Cor. 11,</hi> and it is drawne from the indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or heynouſneſſe of offence in the vnworthy eating and drinking the Lords ſupper in this manner.</p>
               <p>That party, that eateth and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Lords ſupper vnworthily, that is, otherwiſe then it becommeth ſuch a ſupper to be eaten and drunk, peruerting the right and pure vſe thereof, that party is guilty of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud of the Lord, euen as if he ſhould vilely contemne the ſame, and trample it vnder his féete.</p>
               <p>Therefore it behoueth euery one,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:7"/> and euerie one is bound of neceſſitie to examine himſelfe afore hand, how he is fitted to eate and drink the Lords ſupper.</p>
               <p>A fourth reaſon is drawne from the fearefull puniſhment and woe,<note place="margin">The fourth Reaſon.</note> which moſt aſſuredly they doe pull vpon themſelues, who doe eate and drinke the Lords ſupper vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this manner: whoſoeuer eateth and drinketh the Lordes ſupper vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, that partie eateth and drinketh his owne damnation; as our firſt parents in paradiſe did eate their owne death by eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit.</p>
               <p>Therefore, vpon paine of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euerie one is bound of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to examine himſelfe, how hee is prepared to eate and drink the ſame. If you would haue a fift reaſon, it holdeth very ſtrongly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leſſer to the greater, thus:<note place="margin">The fift Reaſon.</note> If in their earthly affaires and buſines, men doe thinke themſelues bound of neceſſity before hand, to examine and make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie
<pb facs="tcp:1920:8"/> as well into the affaires of themſelues, what and of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they be, as into their owne ſelues, how they may finde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues able, fit, and méete to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the ſame, leſt they ſhould take them in hand vnwiſely, in vaine, or with their loſſe and hurt: then who will not much more thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bound of neceſſitie to make the ſame examination, and inquiry in ſpirituall affaires, but eſpecially in this ſo heauenly buſineſſe, the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: wherein we cannot offend with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the high diſpleaſure &amp; diſhonour of our God. Wherein we cannot of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend without the deſerued daunger of eternal condemnation: and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if we conſider the meate &amp; drinke it ſelfe, with other common meates and drinkes, there may no compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſtand betwéen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any reſpect at all.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.55.</note> 
                  <hi>My fleſh is meat indeed, &amp; my bloud is drink indeed (ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt.)</hi> For other meates and
<pb facs="tcp:1920:8"/> drinkes are earthly &amp; corporall, but this is heauenly and ſpirituall. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meate and drinke, whether wée eate and drinke or not, we ſhal ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly die; but this meate and drinke, hée only doth die, which doth not receiue and he doth liue for euer which doth receiue it. Other meate and drinke doth aſſwage hunger and thirſt, but this meate and drinke, I meane ſtill being ſpiritually and by Faith truely receiued, doth more and more ſharpen the ſame, bréeding in vs an inſatiable deſire and longing after them.</p>
               <p>Other meate and drinke, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into the ſubſtance of the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet and drinker; but this,<note place="margin">Not the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements of bread and wine.</note> abiding ſtill the ſame without corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the true religious eaters &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers thereof into it ſelfe, making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of humane, diuine, of carnal, ſpiritual of vngodly minded, to leade a life beſéeming God.<note place="margin">Iohn 6.56.</note> 
                  <hi>For he that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>hee dwelleth in
<pb facs="tcp:1920:9"/> mee,</hi> as a member incorporated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body and braunch, into the vine. <hi>And I in him;</hi> namely, by my ſpirit, whereby he doth liue. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meate and drinke, before they be receiued, are firſt to bee exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, tried, and proued, leſt by any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill condition in them, they hurt vs. But before we preſume to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of this meate and drinke in the Lords ſupper, we muſt firſt examine, try, and proue our ſelues, leſt we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour them, and become hurtfull to our ſelues, through our owne fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I would to God your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were knowne, not vnto mee a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone here by priuate conference, but vnto the whol world alſo by publike writing. For (I think) they are of force not onely to wreſt from the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward and crooked ſpirit, that is, a free confeſsion that it is ſo, but alſo to force out of the hart of flint a floud of teares, to bewaile euery former neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thereof, and further to driue it
<pb facs="tcp:1920:9"/> euer heereafter, diligently and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to put the ſame in practiſe, and neuer in any caſe to omit this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wiſe, and carefull examination of ones ſelfe, before the receiuing of the Lords Supper. But (good Sir) from your preſent ſpeech nowe, mee thinkes, doe ariſe two doubtes more, wherein I pray you ſatisfie mee in a word.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you ſay on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is then the examination of others by the Miniſter, before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Lords Supper forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or needeleſſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>It is more then plaine by the holy ſcriptures, that examination by the Miniſter of thoſe committed to his charge, where néede ſhall be:<note place="margin">Gen. 18. Ioſh. 24. Miniſters, fathers, and houſholders ought to examine their pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, children &amp; ſeruants.</note> by the father of his children, by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his ſeruants, is not onely not forbidden, but ſtraightly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and highly commended, (howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer alas) it bee too careleſly put in practiſe of ſuch as one day wil trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quake to come to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb facs="tcp:1920:10"/> for it.) And ſo much the more commended, if it be done with that care and conſcience that it ought: namely, not for auricular confeſſion, and then all is well, as the Papiſts dreame, or for cuſtome and ſhew: but for to proue, how they knowe their dutie therein, to teach them, if they know it not: yea, and not euen then to thruſt it into their mouthes, when they are to receiue the Supper: but in ſuch due ſeaſon, as they may be ſure to bee perfect in it. Vnto the which examination, as euery Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, father, and maſter is bound: ſo likewiſe is euery pariſhioner, childe, &amp; ſeruant, reuerendly &amp; willingly to ſubmit themſelues therevnto, before they come vnto the Lordes Table. But yet notwithſtanding, this exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination by an other cannot ſecure, neither is any ſafe warrant for any man: for one man may deceiue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; the examined may deceiue the examiner in moſt points, but no man can deceiue the iudgment of his own
<pb facs="tcp:1920:10"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. Though the former exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one man by another be néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, neceſſary, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, &amp; commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; though one be examined by an other a thouſand times, yet the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of ones ſelf, is in no wiſe to be omitted, but carefully to bee held faſt, becauſe it is moſt certain, &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceiue: and therfore the Apoſtle ſaith rather; <hi>Let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> &amp; in an other place;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Examin your ſelues: know ye not your own ſelues?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ob.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You haue fully ſatisfied me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo. But this one queſtion more: Is it not required, that one do examine and inquire into thoſe, with whom he is to communicate, &amp; that he do find them worthily prepared, before hee can ſafely communicate with them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>Hereto I anſwer you:<note place="margin">Some are too buſie examiners and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers into others.</note> that ſome with the Anabaptiſticall ſect, are too buſie ſearchers into others, in the meane while altogether neglecting themſelues. And ſome againe, with theſe Anabaptiſts, imitating thoſe proud ſpirits of the olde <hi>Cathari,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1920:11"/> and after them of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> doe falſly flatter themſelues with a perſwaſion of abſolute and perfect holineſſe in this life, and as I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell, what ſpirits made wholly of the ayre, doe contemne the company and fellowſhip of all men, in whom there doth appeare at any time any manner of humane want or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in this life. And further, if where the Goſpell is preached, there appeare not forthwith fruits of life, anſwerable to the ſame, doe by and by cry out that there is no Church, and therefore they can haue no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie nor fellowſhip, eſpecially at the Lords Supper: whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle did ſéeme alſo to reſpect, when he ſaid; <hi>Let euery one therefore exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> not thoſe with whom he is to communicate; but <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>themſelues.</hi> In the meane while, it is not my meaning to pleaſe any careleſſe Athieſts of theſe times, who ſo ſoone as they ſhall heare, that none can heere in this world
<pb facs="tcp:1920:11"/> liue perfectly, and that GOD doth not impute vnto his faithfull children all their weake infirmities, doe ſtraight way here vpon imagine, that they may ſecurely wallowe in all kinde of malice, miſchiefe, and wickedneſſe. Neyther is it my meaning, to giue liberty of propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lordes Supper vnto any, by their careleſſe and ſenſuall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming to the ſame. For it is to be wiſhed, that euery one, who is manifeſtly knowne to bee an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Adulterer, or Adultereſſe, a forſworne perſon, or a common ſwearer, a Drunkard, an vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table contender, a careleſſe hearer, or a ſcorner of the Word and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry therof, that ſuch like, I ſay,<note place="margin">And ſo they are, if they be complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of.</note> what ſoeuer they be, ſhould by the cenſure and diſcipline of the Church appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, bee excommunitated, baniſhed from the Church of Chriſt, and caſt out of the kingdome: and by that meanes, excluded from the Lordes Supper, vntill they ſhould ſhewe
<pb facs="tcp:1920:12"/> againe manifeſt tokers of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Or if at any time, perhapes through any let &amp; occation, the ſame excommunication cannot readily be had,<note place="margin">And this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is freely permitted. Cannon. 26.</note> that then euery Miniſter, to whome it may properly belong, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing manifeſt knowledge thereof, might bee of <hi>Chriſoſtomes</hi> minde; who ſayd, he would rather ſpend his owne body, then impart the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſignes of Chriſts body vnto ſuch perſones: knowing, that they, who doe willingly, and wittinglie admit them, haue their handes as deepe in prophaning of Gods coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as the impenitent parties the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they doe admit, and alowe them for Gods friendes, who are Gods enimies, and would make God ſuch a one, as hath entred a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, and is in league with Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and Hipocrites. But, to come neerer to your demaund, if any ſuch impenitent ſinners ſo manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne, bee at any time allowed and ſuffered at the Lords table, the
<pb facs="tcp:1920:12"/> blame then muſt and doth reſt vpon thoſe, who haue ſuch authoritie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and keepe them backe. As for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other priuate perſon of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, it cannot hurt him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with ſuch, neither ought their preſence to let him, if by exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of himſelfe, hee find himſelfe fitte, and worthylie prepared there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. For euerie priuate perſon, in this caſe, ſhall render accompt vnto his Lord &amp; maſter, not for others, but for himſelfe. And the Apoſtle ſayeth not, <hi>Let euery man examine</hi> thoſe, with whome they are to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: but, <hi>let euery man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> Neither doth hee ſay, <hi>whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall eate this bread, and drinke this cuppe of the Lord with others,</hi> that be vnworthy, <hi>ſhall be guilty of the body &amp; bloud of the Lord:</hi> But, <hi>whoſoeuer ſhal eate &amp; drink vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyly himſelfe, ſhal be guilty. &amp;c.</hi> So that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing, which ſtands vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery ones ſaluation, or condemnation in this buſines, is <hi>himſelfe</hi> &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues:
<pb facs="tcp:1920:13"/> euery one (I ſay) narrowly and with godly wiſedome to examine and to lift into himſelfe. Wherein ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as haue béene careleſſe hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I counſell them in the feare of God, to looke vnto it hereafter; or elſe to ſtand without anſwer, and excuſe at the day of iudgement, when they would bee full glad to carrie a cléere conſcience therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well then, ſeeing it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſhifted, but that euerie one is bound of neceſsitie to examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, before hee preſume to eate and drinke the Lords Supper: and ſeeing it is his own ſelfe that doth ſo neare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch and concerne euery man: and ſeeing further, that you doe ſo ſtraightly aduiſe euery man, euer hereafter to haue a zealous care ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as of his own ſaluation. To the end this may bee, firſt diligently perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of euery one, I pray you, next now declare, wherin this examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ones ſelfe doth conſiſt; and what it is that euery one muſt examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:1920:13"/> for. And ſecondly, to the end it may be the better and more willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed of euery one: I pray you ſecondly, declare it with as eaſie order, and as briefly as may be. And the rather, becauſe I haue heard ſome vntoward and vnwilling ſpirits (who thinke, that any colour will ſerue them for a iuſt &amp; blameleſſe excuſe) I haue heard them giue out, I ſay, that they knew not where to begin any ſuch examination of themſelues, how to goe forwards in it, and that it is too tedious for their braine, to whom by your good meanes, I hope, this priuat conference ſhall publikely bee made knowne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke your meaning is to haue it ſet downe in a few generall heads, vnder which all other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar duties may be comprehended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That is my meaning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ones ſelfe conſiſteth in three things in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>The examination then of ones ſelfe, doth conſiſt briefly in thrée thinges, that is to ſay, in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:14"/> in faith, in a full purpoſe to liue and practiſe, according to that knowledge and faith: or if you will haue it plainer, thus; Before a man doe eate and drinke the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he muſt examine himſelfe: firſt, whether he haue ſuch knowledge, as he ought to haue. Secondly, whether hee haue faith, to beléeue that hee knoweth. Thirdly, whether he come with a reſolute purpoſe, to liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto that his knowledge and faith. For whoſoeuer ſhall finde in himſelfe theſe thrée, hee may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelfe, that hee dooth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily eate and drinke the Lordes Supper, becauſe they doe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all other particular duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired thereunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt thing, for which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one muſt examine himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he do eate and drinke the Lords Supper (you ſay) is knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Knowledge is neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the firſt in this exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</note>I put knowledge indéede in the firſt place, and (I thinke) verie neceſſarily. For how is it poſſible for
<pb facs="tcp:1920:14"/> any man to take any thing in hand, and doe it aright, except he doe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly know, what belongeth vnto the ſame. Now is it poſſible, that he ſhould eate and drinke the Lordes Supper worthily, who doth not know what is required to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy eating &amp; drinking of the Lordes Supper? when our Sauiour ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Saduces,<note place="margin">Matt. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Yee doe erre not knowing the Scriptures.</hi> Did he not ſay plainely, that the want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was the cauſe of their erring, being deceiued and dealing awry. When the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid;<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy word is a Lanterne vnto my feete and a light vnto my pathes;</hi> did hée not clearely teach, that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the word of God, muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our actions and procéedings, and that without the ſame know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge we walke in darkenes, wee know not what we doe, nor whether we goe? I thinke this is ſo plaine, that it néedes no further diſputing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ob.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why: muſt a plaine ſimple man,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:15"/> that can neuer a letter vppon the booke, come furniſhed with this knowledge, before hee can eate and drinke the Lords Supper? what if ſuch a one ſhould come to you and ſay? The ſcriptures are too buſie for my head, I know how to earne my liuing with the ſweat of my browes, honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; truely, I truſt I know as the reſt of my neighbours know: I hope they meane well, they meane no hurt at their comming to the Lordes Table, nor no more doe I: or ſuch like ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: would not this be ſufficient for him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſw.</speaker>
               <p>I knowe no difference the ſcriptures make in this reſpect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the learned and vnlearned, betwéene the ſimpleſt and the wiſeſt of all, neither yet any diſpenſation the one hath more then the other: but this I know,<note place="margin">Ignorance is no excuſe</note> that ignorance is no excuſe for any, by theſe our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours owne wordes;<note place="margin">Luke, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>But that ſeruant that knew not his Maiſters will, and yet did commit thinges worthy of
<pb facs="tcp:1920:15"/> ſtripes, ſhall bee beaten with fewe ſtripes.</hi> This I know, that none can pleade ignorance: for the Lord God ſpeaketh generally vnto all by his ſeruant <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>The word which I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand thee this day, is not hid from thee, neither is far of: It is not in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that thou needeſt to ſay, Who ſhall aſcend for vs into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fetch it vnto vs, and to declare it vnto vs, that wee may doe it: neither is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſea, that thou needeſt to ſay, who ſhall go ouer the ſea to bring it, and to declare it vnto vs, that we may doe it: but this word is very neare thee, euen in thy mouth and in thine heart to do it.</hi> This I know,<note place="margin">Ioſu. 1.</note> that all ſortes of people ought to know the Scriptures. This I knowe,<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are eaſie to the ſimpleſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing three things</note> that the Scriptures are eaſie vnto the plaine and moſt ſimple people that are, obſeruing but thrée conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>The firſt, if by zealous prayer they ſhall call for the illumination of Gods ſpirit.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1920:16"/>
               <p>The ſecond, if they ſhall beſtowe the like endeuour, care, and ſtudie, to know them, that they doe and can vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cunning fetches for their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profit: whereof if a booke ſhould be framed twiſe as large as the Bible, it would ſoone be knowne euen of the ſimpleſt, yea, though he could neuer a letter on the booke (as you ſay) yet he would haue it at one hand or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it would buſie his head ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a whit. The third, if they ſhall deſire and labour to know the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the end to kéepe the will of the Lord reuealed in them: they are King <hi>Dauids</hi> words; <hi>The Law of the Lord giueth wiſedome vnto the ſimple.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 19. Pro. 14.</note> Wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith; <hi>A ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſeeketh wiſedome, and findeth it not: but knowledge is eaſie to him, that will vnderſtand.</hi> And when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> would perſwade the Lorde, to teach him to knowe his will, hee drawes the Lord, as it were, with this reaſon, becauſe he will kéepe his will; when he knowes it: <hi>Teach me
<pb facs="tcp:1920:16"/> (O Lord) the way of thy ſtatutes, &amp; I will keepe it vnto the end. O giue me vnderſtanding, &amp; I will keepe thy law, yea I will keepe it with my whole heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to conclud, this I knowe, that the ſimpleſt and plaineſt man that is, would bee aſhamed to bee found vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull, and to be taken tardy, in the profeſſion that hee hath taken vppon him. If his knowledge faile in the trade, he was neuer bounde appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice vnto; if his knowledge faile in the Art of <hi>Logick, Rhetorick,</hi> or in the miſterie of <hi>Aſtronomie,</hi> or ſuch like: why in this he is not to bee bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: but if his knowledge faile in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> points of Chriſtianity, whereunto he was bound apprentice in Baptiſme, which hee tooke vpon him to profeſſe at the time of his Baptiſme, and wherin he hath ſerued ſo long appre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip: I thinke, in this hee is worthy to be blamed: I trow, in this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt of vs all would take great ſhame, to be found vnlearned and vnſkilful.
<pb facs="tcp:1920:17"/> If any, intending to receiue the Lords Supper, ſhould come to mée with ſuch anſwer, as you ſay: I know how to earne my liuing with the ſweate of my browes, &amp;c: (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede I thinke too to many hold it for the anſwere of a ſound Chriſtian) ſurely I ſhould bee driuen againſt my will, to reply vppon him againe with theſe words: If this bee all the knowledge that you haue, and looke for, then a bruit beaſt is, for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as good a Chriſtian as you: then a bruit beaſt may for his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (I ſpeake it with reuerence: bee admitted to the Communion as wel as you: for a bruit beaſt knowes how to get his liuing with the ſweat and labour of his body as well as you, and no more doe you looke for. Further, I would reply againe from the Apoſtle <hi>Paul:</hi> You would pretend a zeale and deuotion,<note place="margin">Rom. 10,</note> but the zeale and deuotion of any what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, either to God or godlines, is nothing worth, if it bee not
<pb facs="tcp:1920:17"/> according vnto knowledge.<note place="margin">Zeale with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is condemned</note> If any man intend to goe to any place, hee muſt keepe the way, that leadeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: if any man haue a zeale and deuotion to God, and doe ſeeke God from the heart, of neceſſitie hee muſt keepe the way, that leadeth vnto him, and that way is his word. It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (ſayth Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) to halt in the way, then to runne ſwiftly out of the way. If wee will bee deuout and religious, let vs take it for truth which <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith: That is true religion, zeale, &amp; deuotion, which is ioyned with the word of God. And therefore ſo many as come vnto the Supper of the Lord without the knowledge of this word to inſtruct and tell them, what is here to bee done, and how they ought to deale therein: vndoubtedly they doe fare as they doe, who are blindfolded and haue their eyes cloſed vp.</p>
               <p>A man would wonder,<note place="margin">A moſt fitte ſimilitude,</note> to meete in the high-way, Tenne, Twentie, Thirty, or Fortie people blindfolded
<pb facs="tcp:1920:18"/> grabling to ſome long iournies end: Surely he would thinke them ſtarke mad, euer to take ſuch a iourney in hand in that order: and hee would iudge, that they would either neuer or very hardly at all, come to the place they deſire. Euen ſo in like ſort, when thou ſéeſt people flocke vnto the Lordes Supper without the knowledge of Gods holy word, to direct them, and to ſhew them, how to doe it: behold, thou ſeeſt a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie blindfolded, and thou maieſt as wel thinke them beſides themſelues, euer to take ſuch a matter in hand ſo blindely: and as well thou maieſt iudge and ſay, that they will neuer come to heauen, and to God, to whom they doe trauell, or rather doe but ſéeme to trauell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ob.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe things (I would thinke) are of force, to make euery man rowſe vp himſelfe, and to looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, before hee doe approach vnto Gods Table, but eſpecially the plaine vnlearned man, who (ſilly
<pb facs="tcp:1920:18"/> ſoule) is wont to perſwade himſelfe, if he come thither, with a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and intent, proceeding from a blinde zeale and deuotion, that then hee hath done his dutie very well; Therfore, for his better help &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſhew, I pray you, what meanes hee hath to get this knowledge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him, and to auoid this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ignorance, wherewith hee is wont to come ſo blindfolded to the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſw.</speaker>
               <p>The meanes that euerie rude,<note place="margin">Meanes to attaine to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods word.</note> and ignorant perſon hath to attaine to the knowledge of, and in the word of God, are theſe. Firſt, and principally, they muſt, after the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> as was ſaid before,<note place="margin">The firſt meanes.</note> with ſinglenes of heart in praier, beſéech the Lord to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue from their mindes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that palpable fogge and myſt of their owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall darkeneſſe and ignorance, and to illuminate the ſame with the light of his ſpirit, obſeruing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="tcp:1920:19"/> to pray, firſt, with an earneſt zeale, and affection to the knowledge of this word, ſecondly with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained purpoſe, knowing the ſame, to leade their liues thereafter.<note place="margin">The ſecond meanes.</note> This done, then if they haue a Prophet, which hath that <hi>Vrim</hi> vpon is breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, that is, who is adorned with the light of knowledge, vnto whoſe publique teaching they may reſort: firſt,<note place="margin">Hebr. 6.</note> for their catechiſing, &amp; inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the principles, grounds, and foundation of religion: becauſe in a building order requireth, that firſt of all the foundation be laid: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards for more perfit and ſound doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2,</note> and ſtronger meate, as the building goes forward, and growes towarde perfection, yea, and vnto whome they may haue ſtill recourſe by priuate conference, for to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued of euery doubt: Becauſe (as the Prophet <hi>Malachie</hi> ſayth) <hi>The Prieſtes lippes muſt preſerue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mala. 2.</note> and from him as from Gods ſtore-houſe, they are to haue their
<pb facs="tcp:1920:19"/> wantes ſupplyed. If, I ſay, God hath in his ſuperabundant mercie bleſſed them with ſuch a Prophet and Paſtor, then muſt they not wiſh him out of their coaſtes for dealinge againſt their ſwine: that is againſt thir vncleanneſſe and filthyneſſe, as the <hi>Gergeſenes</hi> wiſhed Chriſt: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt they neglect and abuſe this bleſſing, but with all true thankfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vſe the ſame, and with the <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeller Lidia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 8</note> lend him the hearing withal diligent and reuerent attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; with the cleane beaſtes in the lawe, chew the cudde,<note place="margin">Act. 16 The third meanes Leu. 11</note> that is ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditate vpon whatſoeuer they haue heard and receiued from him, leaſt it goe in at the one eare and out at the other.</p>
               <p>But if there bee no Prophet in Iſraell, if they haue no ſuch Paſtor, vnto whom as vnto a Nurſſe, they may ſo fly for their ſpirituall foode, and ſuſtenance: Then their next remeadie and meanes are, firſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the commaundement of
<pb facs="tcp:1920:20"/> our Sauiour,<note place="margin">The fourth meanes.</note> to pray vnto the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Fountaine of all good giftes, that he would ſend forth labourers into his harueſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.</note> to ſtay the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all famine of bread: that hee would moue the hearts, of thoſe which be in authoritie, to pittie the ſilly ſhéepe of Chriſt, and likewiſe ſtirre vp the hearts of all thoſe, who haue in their hands the planting and placing, yet now at the laſt, while the day doth laſt, to make a conſcience, whom they ſet ouer Gods flocke, and that they wuld become true Patrons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede:<note place="margin">The patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons ought to reſpect the flocke of Chriſt.</note> that is, not ſo much of the man nor Benefite, as of the flocke of Chriſt Ieſus. Secondly, and in the meane while, vntill by the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouidence of the Lorde, the Harueſt may bee ſo furniſhed, theſe ſimple, rude, and ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who cannot reade themſelues, muſt, for knowledge in Gods word, ſpend that time in conference and reaſoning with others,<note place="margin">The fift meanes.</note> either at home, or abroad, at one hand or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:20"/> if they haue a will thereunto, which they are wont idlely, vainely, and vpon vnfruitfull workes many waies to miſſpend.</p>
               <p>And further, they muſt lend their eares to ſuch, as can reade good bookes, Engliſh, and Engliſhed wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wherewith, if they will but ſtep out of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> roade, into <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yeard, the ſtalls ſtand ſo ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yea, and which are in ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance brought home almoſt to their owne doores, whereſoeuer in any place within the Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land they haue their dwelling, that, who ſo doth ſtill remaine ignorant of the way and will of the Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in his word, they muſt néedes be willingly, wilfully, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately ignorant, and ſhall ſurely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the puniſhment of wilfull, ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked, and obſtinate perſons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all excuſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doubtleſſe you haue ſaid very well, that the firſt thing which euerie one muſt examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:21"/> before they preſume to come vnto the Lords Table, is knowledge. You haue likewiſe proued, that this knowledge is required at the hands of euery one, learned and vnlearned, wiſe and ſimple, and that no man hath any diſpenſation, or tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to come thither ignorantly, more then an other. You haue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhewed the meanes, whereby euerie one may come by it, if they will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But now, I pray you, in the meane time, omit not to ſhew in briefe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, wherein this knowledge dooth conſiſt, or what bee the particulars, which euery one muſt know, before they can be worthy partakers of the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An.</speaker>
               <p>The matter it ſelfe, we haue in hand, is good and godly, and through Gods bleſſing may hereafter tend to his glorie, and the encreaſe of his Church. Beſides, it I ſhould waxe wearie, yet your forward deſire and willingnes to learne, would ſtirre
<pb facs="tcp:1920:21"/> vp and encourage me to goe on. If all, that be ignorant, woulde take your courſe, ſurely all might come to knowledge néedefull vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I wiſh, your example might not be lightly paſſed ouer. You haue had mine indeuour hitherto, and you ſhall likewiſe haue it in this if God permit.</p>
               <p>You would learne further (you ſay) what knowledge euerie one by examination of themſelues muſt finde in themſelues, before they can bee worthy partakers of the Lordes Supper. And herein, according to your owne Chriſtian motion, I would rather ſéeke to profit many by plaine order, then to pleaſe a few by curious art and cunning diuiſion. For your demaund therefore: this knowledge doubtleſſe, I cannot ſée, where it can begin with that profit and order, that it ought elſe,<note place="margin">The degrees of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Lords Supper.</note> then at mans creation, for the firſt degrée thereof. And therefore before I doe preſume to come vnto the Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:1920:22"/> ſupper: I muſt find my ſelfe to know particularly &amp; in order to this effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</note>The firſt, that in my firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> the Lord God created mee and all mankinde, in ſoule according to his owne image and likeneſſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 1</note> in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, in body without fault or blemiſh: in a word, both in ſoule and body, a moſt glorious creature, furniſhed with all heauenlie and glorious prerogatiues, able of my ſelfe to doe the will of my God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any kinde of contradiction,<note place="margin">Mans firſt eſtate glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> or check, which might come from any imperfection, either of ſoule or body: which was my firſt eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond degree of knowledge.</note>The ſecond, That becauſe good reaſon it was, I ſhould acknowledg a Lord aboue my ſelfe, euen my al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie and mercifull Creator, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame my Lord &amp; God gaue me an eaſie commaundement, to kéep and obey:<note place="margin">Gen. 2</note> namely, that I ſhould not eate of the fruit of one onely Tree in Paradice, the tree of the knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:1920:22"/> of good and euill, vpon paine, if I did eate, to dye the death.</p>
               <p>The third,<note place="margin">The third degree of knoledge.</note> that the conſideration neither of the infinite goodneſſe and mercie of my maker, neither of my moſt perfect and free eſtate, neither of the eaſines of the commandement, nor yet the puniſhment threatned for the breach of it, could make me bolde me faſt by God, and to the obedience of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements. But (wretch that I was) I muſt needs forſake my maker, and ſubiect my ſelfe vnto the obedience of the Diuel my deſtroyer: and ſo, accordinge to his damnable wil and word, I muſt eate of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruite,<note place="margin">Gen. 3</note> of the Tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good &amp; euil. Wherby indéed I came to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledg of the good loſt, &amp; the euill found (for ſo the Diuell iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ingly meant) which I leaſt thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f: wherby I loſt al former good, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, perfection, and freedome both of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ody and ſoule, and found all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of euill, ignominy, imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hraldome, both of body and ſoule:
<pb facs="tcp:1920:23"/> whereby I made my ſelfe vnable, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie part euer afterward alſo to kéepe the commandement of my God, or to ſteppe any righteous ſteppe at all, whereby in a word, I did caſt my ſelfe downe headlong from the top of all happines, into the depth of all miſery in this life, and into the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal gulfe of endleſſe torment &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the world to come,<note place="margin">Mans ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond eſtate wretched.</note> which was my ſecond eſtate, and of al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before you go any further, I pray you ſuffer me one word. It ſeemes to me that this knowledge of mans firſt and ſecond eſtate, makes little to the worthy receiuing of the Lordes Supper, becauſe it belongs not vnto the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>I doe not ſay, that theſe my two former eſtates are any part of the Lords Supper, or that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long either to the benefit or vſe of the Supper it ſelfe; but that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them muſt bring mee, by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto the knowledge of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite
<pb facs="tcp:1920:23"/> and vſe of the Lords Supper. For before I can truely know and confeſſe any benefit and reſtoring in Chriſt, I muſt firſt knowe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that I was in miſerie: before I doe flie vnto Chriſt for ſuccour, I will firſt knowe ſome reaſon why, and that I haue néede of ſuccour, and what driues me vnto Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now, the Law,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> which layes before me my miſerie, ſinne, vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and eternal damnation, becauſe I cannot now, through my fall, and diſobedience kéepe it; <hi>It is (ſaith the Apoſtle) a Schoolemaiſter or Vſher,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>which ſendes mee vnto Chriſt;</hi> for righteouſnes and ſaluation in him. And therefore theſe two former e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, are as it were the Alphabet, <hi>A, B, C,</hi> or firſt entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, where I muſt firſt begin in the ſchoole of God, and which I muſt firſt knowe out of his word, before I can come either order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or profitably vnto any riper know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that good &amp; benefit which is offered me in Chriſt, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently in his holy ſupper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1920:24"/>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I doe now ſee your courſe, and order right well: it is right plaine and profitable, I pray you, go on vnto the fourth point.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aunſ.</speaker>
               <p>The fourth point of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which by examination of my ſelfe, I muſt find my ſelfe to knowe, before I come vnto the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,<note place="margin">The fourth degree of knowledge.</note> is to this effect. Namely, that the Lord God on the one ſide, becauſe hee would, and muſt haue his iuſtice ſatiſfied for my ſinne, and the ſinne of all mankind, which iuſtice requireth, that as true and very man, had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt God: ſo of neceſſitie, true, and very man, muſt ſatiſfie his iuſtice with death, and tormentes both of body and ſoule for that ſinne, according to the ſentence of his iuſt word.<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. 2.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Mans third &amp; laſt eſtate reſtored by Chriſt.</note> And of the other ſide, becauſe hee would in this his iuſtice become mercifull vnto man too, hath in his rich wiſdome, cauſed his only ſonne being very God, to take my nature vpon him, and to become alſo very man: who in the ſame his humane
<pb facs="tcp:1920:24"/> nature, might ſatiſfie GODS iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for my ſinne, by death, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes due vnto mee for the ſame: and by vertue and power of his God-head might be able to ſuſtaine, and beare in his fleſh the wrath and puniſhment, might bee able to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me alſo from the ſame, and might repaire in mee, and reſtore vnto mee againe that righteouſneſſe, life, and bleſſedneſſe, which I had loſt by my fall, and diſobedience: which his mercie the Lord firſt ſet a broach in Paradice, after that hee publiſhed the ſame by his Patriarkes, and Prophets: Thirdly, he ſhadowed it out, by ſacrifices, and ceremonies of the Lawe: and laſtly, fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed it by the ſame his owne only ſonne.</p>
               <p>The fift poynte of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">The fift degree of knowledge.</note> which by examination of my ſelfe I muſt finde in my ſelfe, beefore I come to the Lordes Supper is, that as GOD doth thus offer, and reach out his hande<pb facs="tcp:1920:25"/> of mercie vnto mee,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2</note> ſo likewiſe I muſt haue another hand to take it: it is my parte to apprehend,<note place="margin">As God hath a hand to giue, ſo we muſt haue a hand to take.</note> to take and lay hold vpon the ſame with the hande of faith, as the onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall cauſe of my ſaluation, leaſt it bee alledged againſt mee, <hi>I would,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23</note> 
                  <hi>but you would not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, and to come neerer the matter: before I come vnto the Lordes Supper, by <hi>examination</hi> of my ſelfe I muſt finde my ſelfe to knowe,<note place="margin">The ſixt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of knowledge.</note> that the Lorde God hath ordayned and inſtituted helpes, and ſeales to ſtrengthen and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this my faith, in that his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy promiſed and offered in his ſonne: namely his word, and two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of knowledge.</note>In the ſeauenth place, by <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> I muſt find my ſelfe to know, before I preſume to come vnto the Sacrament of the Lordes Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: that in a Sacrament two things are to be conſidered.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1920:25"/>
               <p>The firſt is a viſible and outward ſigne, the ſecond an inuiſible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward grace ſignified thereby: And in the ſacrament of baptiſme, the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and outward ſigne to be, <hi>water,</hi> ſprinckled vpon the bodie of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie baptized, to the waſhing away of the filthines of the bodie: The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible or inward grace ſignified thereby, to bee the bloud of Chriſt ſprinkled vpon the ſoule by faith, wrought by the holy Ghoſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſpirituall filthines of the ſoule is waſhed away and forgiuen, the righteouſnes of Chriſt imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the partie, the olde man of ſinne mortified and ſlaine, the new man of righteouſnes raiſed vp and reuiued, anſwerable vnto the death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt: by which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the Lord firſt of all doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit vs into his Church and family.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the Sacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſupper, the viſible and outward ſignes therein to bee: Firſt <hi>bread,</hi> broken and eaten, ſecondly <hi>wine</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed
<pb facs="tcp:1920:26"/> and drunke the inuiſible and inward Grace ſignified thereby to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Firſt the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and crucified, Secondly the bloud of Chriſt ſhed for to pacifie Gods wrath, and to ſatiſfie his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for my ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Againe, that thereby is ſignified a full ſatiſfaction of Gods iuſtice, and a perfect ſaluation purchaſed, without any thing wanting, becauſe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread is broken, ſignifying his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy crucifyed, but alſo wine is diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted, ſignifying his bloud ſhed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly: that thereby is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the violence of Chriſtes death, his ſoule being drawne and ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his bodie, becauſe there is ſeene breaking and diuiſion of bread.</p>
               <p>Fourthly: That thereby is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied our <hi>Vnion,</hi> vniting and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into one bodie and nature with Chriſt (receiuing him by faith) euen as ſurely and as certainely, as the bread, and wine, which wee eate,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:26"/> and drinke in the Lordes Supper, are vnited, and grow into one bodie &amp; nature with vs. And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſéeing ſo by faith we become the true members of Chriſt, Bone of his bone, and fleſhe of his fleſhe, and doe growe into one bodie with him, euen as <hi>Eue,</hi> being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and taking of the ſubſtance of the bodie of <hi>Adam</hi> her huſband, became as it were parte of him, nay one fleſhe with him. That therefore (I ſay) it muſt needes follow of neceſſitie,<note place="margin">Chriſt his Members muſt needs liue by his ſpirit.</note> that wee muſt take life from, and bee gouerned by one and the ſelfe ſame ſpirit of Chriſt, as all the members of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy take life from,<note place="margin">Iohn 6. Iohn 15.</note> and are gouerned by one, and the ſame ſoule.</p>
               <p>Wherupon if followeth neceſſarily againe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo many as haue not a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care, in their liues, &amp; conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to expreſſe the fruits, &amp; graces of the holy ſpirit, but do ſtil delight, ſlauiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſerue Satan &amp; ſinne, ſo many do in vaine flatter themſelues, that
<pb facs="tcp:1920:27"/> they are the members of Chriſt, and that they haue receiued Chriſt in his holy ſupper, his death and paſſion, to the forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes: Becauſe Chriſt cannot bee drawne from his ſpirit, neither receiued without his ſpirit, but he, that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his body, and drinketh his bloud truly by faith, muſt needs eate and drinke his ſpirit alſo, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently expreſſe the fruits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſpirit, in a regenerate life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe (I ſay) who ſo doe eate the bodie, and drinke the bloud of Chriſt crucified, and ſhed vpon the croſſe truely, by faith, to the forgiuenes of their ſinnes, they are members vnited vnto Chriſt, they are grafted into Chriſt, they dwel in Chriſt, and Chriſt in them. And they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are grafted into Chriſt, muſt néeds take part of, and liue by the ſpirit, and life, which is in Chriſt, euen as the branches which are grafted into the wine, do participate and liue of the ſap and life of the vine.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1920:27"/>
               <p>In the fift and laſt place, by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of my ſelfe, I muſt find my ſelfe to know, that, whereas we doe feede not of ſundry kindes of bread, and drinke, not of ſundrie cuppes, but al of vs of one bread and one cup in regard of the inſtitution and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, hereby is taught and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied our vnity and communitie one with another alſo, that we ought to be of one bodie, that we ought mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to loue one another, as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one bodie, and as thoſe, which are fed and nouriſhed by one bodie, by one meate, by one drinke.</p>
               <p>Here in this Sacrament all are one, and one is all. All come to one, and one is made of all. For in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect, we ſee, of many graines of corne is made one bread, of many grapes is made one wine: whereby is ſignified further, that an eſpeciall end and drift of this Sacrament is, of the multitude of the faithfull, as of many members to make one bodie, and to knit them togither in one mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="tcp:1920:28"/> relation and loue.</p>
               <p>It is reported by <hi>Saluſt</hi> a noble hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Hiſtoriographer, that they, which conſpired with <hi>Catiline</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Rome, dranke all of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand mans bloud, whereby they would all make (as it were) a Conſanguinity and affinitie among themſelues, whereby they would all bind themſelues, to will one thing, all to meane and doe one thing, and not any one to open the conſpiracie, or to diſagree one from another in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſort, &amp; therein they iumped &amp; ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together euen vnto the death.</p>
               <p>Now, can the drinking of a mortall mans bloud, ſo inuented by mans malice, in a wicked practiſe of a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of men, make one man: of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men, make one body, one mind, one will, one conſent one heart, and bring all to an vnity? And ſhall not the drinking of the bloud of Chriſt, by faith, nay, the eating of his fleſhe alſo, found out by the endles wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; goodnes of God for mans redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:28"/> make all one, Firſt with Chriſt, ſecondly, one with another: make all one body, make one mind, one will, one conſent, one heart, and bring all to an vnity in Chriſtian loue, mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all affection, and brotherly charitie, one with another? which is the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me and whole ſcope of all chriſtian Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie and wiſedome.</p>
               <p>Surely light cannot agree with darkeneſſe, nor the ſpirit of God, with the ſpirit of <hi>Belial,</hi> No more can diuiſion and diſcord agrée with vnitie.</p>
               <p>This Sacrament is a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vnity, therefore it cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, neither admit a clouen heart, diuided from his brother. And thus as by the Sacrament of Baptiſme, our God doth admit vs into his houſe and family, not as ſeruants, but as children: So likewiſe by this Sacrament of the Lordes Supper, as a prouident Father, doth hee féede, and nouriſh vs in the ſame, with the liuing breade of his
<pb facs="tcp:1920:29"/> deare ſonne vnto a true and bleſſed immortalitie.</p>
               <p>And this is the knowledge briefly, for which euery one muſt <hi>examine</hi> themſelues, before they preſume to the Lords ſupper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But you ſaid in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of our ſpeech, that this <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> doth conſiſt in three thinges. In the firſt place, you haue well and neceſſarily placed <hi>knowledge,</hi> I pray you therefore proceede vnto the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Faith is the ſecond thing for which we muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee come to the Lords Supper.</note>I ſaid, that the ſecond thing, for which euery one muſt <hi>examine</hi> themſelues, before they do eate and drinke the Lords ſupper, is <hi>faith.</hi> And ſurely <hi>faith</hi> comes as neceſſarily in the ſecond place, as <hi>knowledge</hi> came in the firſt. For as there can bee no faith without knowledge, ſo again to bare knowledge can be to no purpoſe without faith, that is, except one do beléeue that, hee knoweth in Gods word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Explaine it, I pray you a
<pb facs="tcp:1920:29"/> little more plainely, what faith doe you meane?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſw.</speaker>
               <p>I meane not an <hi>Hiſtorical faith</hi> which is but only a bare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the hiſtorie of thoſe things which are contained in Gods booke,<note place="margin">Faith Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall.</note> aſſenting alſo vnto the truth of them, which faith the very diuels haue, and would gladly haue it vtterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct and put out.<note place="margin">Iames 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I meane not a <hi>Temporarie faith,</hi> which ſteps a ſtep higher, that is, which doth not only know, and giue aſſent vnto the truth of Gods word,<note place="margin">Faith tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie.</note> but doth alſo profes the ſame, yea and ioy thereinto, yet it is but for a ſmall time (as ſaith our Sauiour) and not becauſe it hath any hartie and liuely feeling of Grace offered in the word neither, but for other by cauſes, as vaine glory,<note place="margin">Mat. 17. 1. Cor. 13.</note> worldly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and ſuch like. I meane not a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Faith by Miracles.</note> whereby through di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine reuelation, a man may be ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, that through diuine power hee can remoue mountaines,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:30"/> or worke other miracles.<note place="margin">Faith iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and a true difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition thereof.</note> But I meane that ſweet <hi>Iuſtifying faith,</hi> which doth not onely know, giue conſent, and profes: But which is further, a grounded and reſolued aſſurance of Gods frée promiſe of Grace in Ieſus Chriſt, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſealed in my heart by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt through the meanes of the Goſpell, works of neceſſitie my regeneration, &amp; conuerſion from the old <hi>Adam,</hi> vnto a new creature, from the workes of darkenes, vnto the works of light, &amp; righteous obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your meaning is now plaine. Before one preſumeth to bee partaker of the Lordes Supper, hee muſt <hi>examine himſelfe:</hi> Firſt for <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Secondly for a <hi>Iuſtifying</hi> faith: But by your leaue (good ſir) a word: If this Iuſtifying faith doth alwaies ſhew forth the fruits of regeneration, conuerſion, and righteous obedience, in that partie, whomeſoeuer it doth poſſes, what needs then, any further examination? I meane, what needes
<pb facs="tcp:1920:30"/> a man <hi>examine</hi> himſelfe for a third point, namely, whether hee findeth in himſelfe a reſolute purpoſe, to practiſe according to that his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; faith, in the reſt of his life?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>I anſwere you thus. Too too many do blindly, &amp; hypocritically i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the outward profeſſion of their beliefe, namely the Apoſtles créed, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out all reſpect had vnto life &amp; maners, is a true iuſtifying &amp; ſauing faith which indéed is but a dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kas of faith, as a dead man, wanting both life &amp; ſpirit, is no true man but a dead carkas of a man: now therfore leaſt any man examining himſelfe for faith, ſhould deceiue himſelf with ſuch a faith, &amp; againe, becauſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſhould haue vnto himſelfe, and alſo ſhewe vnto others a ſure marke and euidence of a iuſtifying faith, without all deceipt: I haue added hereunto this third poynt of <hi>examination,</hi> Namely, that euery one ſhould <hi>examine</hi> themſelues alſo, whether they come vnto the Lordes<pb facs="tcp:1920:31"/> Supper, in ſinceritie, and ſinglenes of heart, all hypocriſie laid aſide, with a reſolute purpoſe in the reſt of their liues, to practiſe and liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame their knowledge and faith, that is, with a reſolute purpoſe, to abhorre and flie ſin, and to embrace godlineſſe throughout their whole life. For to this end the Apoſtle <hi>Iames,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iames 2.</note> reaſoning very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely, ſeemeth to make a double iuſtification of man, the one from God, the other from man him ſelfe. God apparantly ſées &amp; knowes as all things elſe viſible, &amp; inuiſable, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, &amp; earthly, ſo the iuſtifying faith of uery man, how it is ſeated in his heart, without any helpes, markes, or tokens, for it ſelfe, and in it ſelfe, without all other reſpects, iuſtifying the man. But to man this faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purely ſpirituall, cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his faithfull markes and fruites be ſéene and knowne, with flat &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute aſſurance, no not to him that hath it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1920:31"/>
               <p>Therefore as God doth iuſtifie a man by his faith, ſo a man muſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie himſelfe by his workes, that is, his faithfull actions, and workes muſt reſolue him, and proue vnto him, that he is poſſeſſed of a true iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith, allowed and approued of God, leaſt otherwiſe he be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a ſhadow &amp; viſard of faith.<note place="margin">Iames 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The wordes of the Apoſtle are plaine, firſt hee ſaith, <hi>ſhew mee thy faith by thy works, &amp; I wil ſhew thee my faith by my workes:</hi> Secondly, <hi>was not Abraham our father iuſtified by workes?</hi> That is, knowne by his workes before men, to haue a iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith before God, <hi>when he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Iſaac his ſonne vpon the Altar.</hi> Thirdly, ye ſée that a man is iuſtified by workes, and not by faith onely, namely of man.</p>
               <p>By which places of the Apoſtle it is clearer then the noone day, that his iuſtifying faith cannot be known vnto man, but by his workes: That (I ſay) his reſolute purpoſe to leade
<pb facs="tcp:1920:32"/> a godly, and a Chriſtian life, &amp; indéed the due execution of the ſame, muſt ſhew and make it euident both vnto himſelfe and vnto others y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſoule is poſſeſſed of a iuſtifying faith before God: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this his <hi>examination</hi> of himſelfe, he is not deceiued, &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that he eateth, and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Lords ſupper worthily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods glory, and his owne euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting comfort.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This alſo nowe is very plaine. This third point of <hi>examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is doubtleſſe as neceſſarie, as the other two: and comes (me thinks) in a comely and diuine order. I haue but one demand more (good ſir) for a full concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>Say on I pray you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Obiect.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do heare your ſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preachers of the word daily tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, (and I beleeue aſſuredly, that you teach truly,) that a true <hi>iustifying faith</hi> doth alwayes bring foorth the fruits of regeneration, newneſſe of life, and righteous obedience, and
<pb facs="tcp:1920:32"/> doth alwayes declare it ſelfe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly by workes in the partie, whom it doth poſſeſſe. I know alſo, that, that notable inſtrument of Gods glory the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, obſerueth the like order, and teacheth the very ſame, who, after that he hath firſt of all ſoundly layd downe the doctrine of faith, and ſtrongly proued, that by only faith in the merits of Chriſt a man is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſaued: Then next of all he commeth vnto exhortation, to manners and integritie of life, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by plainely affirming as much as you ſay: Namely, that Chriſtians muſt adorne their faith and profeſſion with good workes, and that a true iuſtifying faith is euer abundantly fruitfull in the ſame good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nay that which is more: I doe know, that many zealous chriſtians, euen now in our times doe confirme the ſame doctrine by their liues and liuings, who as they do dayly pray for a true iuſtifying faith, and
<pb facs="tcp:1920:33"/> conſtantly profeſſe themſelues to haue the ſame, ſo do they alſo walke in all chriſtian and dutiful obedience to the commandements of God, euer endeuoring themſelues to doe well, and to do good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So that when I do lay their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, of a iuſtifying faith on the one ſide, and their liues on the other ſide together, (me thinks) it doth ſtrongly proue, this doctrine to be alwayes infallibly true: That a true iuſtifying faith, and good workes, are inſeperable, and not to be found aſunder, no more then the Sunne can be without his light, or fire his heate. This (I ſay) I do heare, this I do know, both by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and examples of theſe times, and this I do hold for truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But (the truth is) my ſelfe as many thouſands moe, do not yet in reaſon ſee, how it doth come to paſſe. My laſt ſuite therefore vnto you is, that you would prooue by ſome-ſound reaſons, that a iuſtifying faith, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:1920:33"/> it doth reſt, muſt needes bee effectuall, and fruitfull, in holineſſe of life, &amp; good workes: For doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe though it be the truth, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not clearely ſee it by manifeſt arguments and reaſons, a great number cannot tell, whether they ſhould beleeue it or not. And therefore though they haue but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a bare <hi>Historicall</hi> faith without all reſpect vnto workes and manners, yet they flatter themſelues, that the ſame is a true iuſtifying faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they were able to conuince them ſelues by ſound reaſons, many of them (I am perſwaded) would be as ready to forſake their error, they would be as willing to embrace the true iuſtifying faith, and to expreſſe the ſame, by all dutifull obedience to the commandements of God in their liues, as euer they were to maintaine a bare Hiſtoricall faith with looſeneſſe of life. And now I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anſ.</speaker>
               <p>If you deſire my anſwer for
<pb facs="tcp:1920:34"/> your reſolution, then marke it well.<note place="margin">None can throughly know what a iuſtifying faith is, but he onely that hath it</note>
               </p>
               <p>As no man can vnderſtand or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what hony, and his ſéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is, though you ſpeake neuer ſo much thereof, ſaue he only that hath ſéene and taſted it: <hi>7.</hi> So no man can vnderſtand, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend, what a iuſtifying faith, and the force ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, ſaue he onely, that hath it, and doth beléeue: And as hee that hath ſéene and taſted hony,<note place="margin">A iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith it ſelfe is the beſt reaſon of all other to proue the effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al working of the ſame We beleue not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding but we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</note> néeds no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to proue vnto him the ſwéetnes thereof, ſo he which hath a iuſtifying faith, and doth beléeue, néeds no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to proue vnto him, the effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all force, and working of the ſame, it will proue and ſhew it ſelfe. Neither comes a man by reaſon, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to faith, and to beléeue, but rather by beléeuing hée comes to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: For in humaine Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and matters of the world, we will firſt by the light of reaſon vnderſtand the matter to be ſo, and then afterward wee will beleeue it: But in ſpiritual things, and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:1920:34"/> myſteries, faith goes before rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and vnderſtanding comes after.</p>
               <p>For here by the light of the word we doe beléeue thoſe things, which neither ſence can perceiue, cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conceiue, nor vnderſtanding of the mind comprehend, without the word.</p>
               <p>And hence it was,<note place="margin">Iohn 3. Iohn 20.</note> that <hi>Nichode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> and <hi>Thomas,</hi> were ſo ſharpely reprooued of our Sauiour Chriſt, euen becauſe they would not beléeue, except they might bee brought vnto it by their naturall reaſon and ſence. Now therefore, the ſumme of mine anſwere to your demaund is this.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if a iuſtifying faith doth not ground it ſelfe, vpon the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, to doe that it doth, and to beleeue that it doth beléeue, but doth effectually worke, and do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it doth, of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e without reaſon, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>city of man: Then ſurely it is impoſſible to ſhew the effectuall force, and working of the ſame, by arguments, and proofes of any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<pb facs="tcp:1920:35"/> Secondly, if none can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, what a iuſtifying faith, and force thereof is, but hee onely that hath it, and doth beléeue: then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he, that hath it not, cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the ſanctified force and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſame, in the life and conuerſation, by all the reaſons in the world, to him they are all in vaine.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if a iuſtifying faith, bee reaſon ſufficient of it ſelfe, and the beſt reaſon of all other, to proue the effectuall working thereof in the life of that partie, whomſoeuer it doth poſſeſſe: Then what needs a man to ſeeke further.</p>
               <p>Then for him which ſeekes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to proue, that a iuſtifying faith muſt néeds be fruitful in a godly life, and workes, The beſt courſe is, to procure vnto him, this iuſtifying faith it ſelfe, which (as all other good graces, and gifts beſides) is had and obtained by that ſtrong and euer preuailing meanes with the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:35"/> faithfull, feruent,<note place="margin">The neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the Canker of Religion.</note> and diligent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the neglect and colde practiſe whereof is the decay, and <hi>Canker</hi> of all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:36"/>
            <head>A Prayer and meditation before <hi>the receiuing of the holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in no wiſe to be forgotten <hi>in thy Chamber priuatly.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Eternall, almightie, and moſt mercifull Father, which of thy tender mercie to thy children, haſt alwaies fed them with ſpiritual and heauenly food, féeding to bleſſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, which is the bread of life, and this bread of life is thy ſonne, as it is written <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.5. <hi>ver.</hi> 35. I am the bread of life, which came downe from heauen: he that cometh to me ſhall not hunger in any wiſe, and hée that beléeueth in mee ſhall neuer thirſt, and the bread which I ſhall giue, is my fleſh: which I will giue for the life of the world.</p>
            <p>O moſt ſwéet bread, heale thou my ſicke ſoule, and féeble heart, that I may taſt the ſwéetneſſe of thy loue: heale mee of all mine infirmities, that I delight in no faireneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thée.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1920:36"/>
            <p>I doe acknowledge, O Lord, that I am not worthy the leaſt of all thy mercies, and moſt vnworthy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thée vnder the roofe of my ſoule, by participating thy moſt precious body and bloud. For horrible are the ſins wherewith I am defiled Woe is me Lord, for I am a man of pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lippes, and dwell among people that haue vncleane hearts. And yet againe, my heart is wonderfully lightned when I call into mind, that thou the déere ſonne of Almightie God, cameſt not into this world to call the righteous, but the ſinners to repentance: for they that bee whole neede not the Phyſition, but the ſick: I humbly therefore beſeech thee, O Lord, by thy holy ſpirit, to worke that in my heart, which I cannot worke in my ſelfe, of my ſelfe: though I can try for my belly meat, from meate, and for my purſſe, coyne from coyne, yet can I not proue and try my conſcience, ſo full of blindnes and ſelfe-loue am I, &amp; yet this tryall
<pb facs="tcp:1920:37"/> is required, and muſt be had of true <hi>Communicantes.</hi> I beſeech thee ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue me grace, that afore I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to come to the participation thereof, I may examine my ſelfe by calling my ſinnes to mind, ſearching out my waies, and confeſſing my ſinnes: I may by harty repentance returne vnto thee my Lord, leaſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe by concealing my ſinnes with <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor, I eate but the bread of the Lord, againſt the Lord. Power into mee a true and liuely faith, that I neuer miſtruſt thy word annexed to thy Sacraments, which promiſeth vnto mankind, the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes: for to eate and drinke with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth only, is to no purpoſe: But faith muſt come thereunto and apprehend the word, with the promiſes annexed, for they are the grounds and principles of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: O Lord ſtrengthen my faith and helpe me, ſo to vſe thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacraments, that my weakneſſe may be helped, true loue and charity
<pb facs="tcp:1920:37"/> increaſed, my ſinfull life amended, &amp; my ſoule comforted, through Chriſt my Sauiour, to whome with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the holy ſpirit, bee aſcribed all honour, power, and glory, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A thankſgiuing after the receiuing <hi>of the holy Communion, eſpecially to</hi> be vſed in thy Chamber priuatly.</head>
            <p>AS thou haſt (O Lord) giuen me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pledges of thy loue, euen thy holy Sacraments, and as thou haſt giuen me faith effectually to receiue them, ſo good Lord giue me thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirit &amp; grace, to be hartily thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, leaſt I be like the nine vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful leapers which our Sauiour clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: But rather let me follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe counſell of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Sirach:</hi> Aboue al things giue thanks to him that made thée, and hath repleniſhed thée with his goods: and what are theſe goods, euen all that I haue, or may haue, either te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall, or eternal, either w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in me, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out me, aboue or beneath me, all is the Lords, &amp; of his
<pb facs="tcp:1920:38"/> mercy I haue them, for this bleſſed meate, which thou haſt in thy great mercy left to thy Church, and to me as one of thy members, doth truely witnes that my body ſprinkled with the vertue of thy quickning fleſh, as it were with celeſtiall dew, ſhall riſe againe vnto immortality and euerlaſting glory. O moſt pretious and heauenly treaſures, more to be deſired then all the faire gold and pearles in the world. Let me neuer doubt of the forgiunes of my ſinnes, which thou aſſureſt me of by thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud in thy holy couenant, concluded in thy laſt ſupper, by the breaking of bread, and giuing forth the cup to thy choſen diſciples, and by them to as many as are incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into thy Church. So that no tribulation nor anguiſh, nor perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, neither, hunger, nor naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, neither perils, nor ſworde, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death nor life, may ſeperate me from my heade, whereupon beeing made faſt by this holy ſacrament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb facs="tcp:1920:38"/> I as a liuing member do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende. And I beſeech thee, O Lord, at my reſurrection, from death, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point me a place at thy heauenly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, where I may taſt the new wine in the kingdome of thy father, abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thine elect Angels, and bleſſed Saints for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <closer>Amen</closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
